Register of the Mstislav Nikolaevich Ivanitskii Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Mstislav Nikolaevich Ivanitskii collection,
1921-1945
2000C118
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Writings and miscellany, relating to Russian military activities during World War I and the Russian Civil War. Includes memoirs of S. I. Ver.
Ivanitskii, M. N. (Mstislav Nikolaevich), collector.
Microfilm shelf
Shelf 16.182
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
The Ivanitskii collection contains materials relating primarily to the Russian Civil War in the Far East and émigré military writings. Of particular interest are the memoirs of S. I. Ver relating to his experiences in the First World War, entitled "Iz vospominanii o voine."
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Biography
M.N. Ivanitskii was born in Perm', Russia. Following the Revolution, he and his family emigrated to China, then to Canada, where he completed his high school education, and then to the United States, where he studied at the University of Washington and received a B.A. at the University of California and an M.A. from the Monterey Institute of International Studies.
During the Second World War, he worked as a shipbuilder, and used his savings to buy a printing shop and establish a publishing house called Delo. Russian books, periodicals, bulletins, progams, catalogs, and other printed matter were his stock in trade. In this business he met a significant number of émigrés and collected materials about them.
Ver, S. I.; Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- S. I. Ver File, 1927-1945 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Writings (memoirs and articles), arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1921-1923 (Box 1)
  Bulletins, order and clipping, arranged alphabetically by heading
- S. I. VER FILE, 1927-1945 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - General, 1938-1942 (Folder 1: 1)
      Brief reviews of international affairs
    - "Vospominaniia iz voiny 1914-1918,"., 1927 (Folder 1: 2)
      Typescript and printed copy of portion of memoirs published in Viestnik O-va russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny
    - Review of Russkie v Kalifornii, 1935 October 20 (Folder 1: 3)
      Typescript
    - "Mirovaia voina 1914 g.,"., 1935 December 14 - 1938 April 16 (Folder 1: 4)
      Typescript and holograph. Series of brief writings relating to Russian mobilization and military concepts in the First World War
    - "Nabrosok (1933 g.): K voprosu o vossozdanii Russkoi Armii,"., 1945 September (Folder 1: 5)
  - Subject file. Soviet Union. Raboche-krestianskaia krasnaia armiia--Biography. (Folder 1: 6)
    Brief dossiers on Soviet generals, with some information provided by émigré officers who knew them personally before 1917
- SUBJECT FILE, 1921-1923
  - Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Voennyi flot. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes issues of bulletin of the Siberian flotilla entitled Russkii listok (1923), as well as a biographical article on the commander of the flotilla, Admiral G. K. Stark, and a draft of his final order disbanding the flotilla (24 May 1923)
  - Ungern-Shternberg, Roman Fedorovich, Baron. (Folder 1: 8)
    Clipping from the Vladivostok Daily News (15 October 1921) describing his trial